Guide to the Katharine F. Lenroot Papers
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Katharine F. Lenroot Papers
1909-1974.
Lenroot, Katharine F. (Katharine Fredrica), 1891-1982.
13.4 linear ft. (32 document boxes and 1 flat box)
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library, New York, NY 10027
MS#0767
4079022
This collection contains correspondence, research files, speeches, writings and other records related to Katharine F. Lenroot, a child welfare leader and the third Chief of the United States Children's Bureau (1934-1951). Lenroot served the Children's Bureau from its earliest years, and contributed significantly to the bureau's development during the New Deal and to the establishment of United Nations International Children's Emergency Fund after World War II. Most of the Papers relate to her professional career, and materials dating from her Washington years comprise the largest part of this collection. After her retirement Lenroot continued to devote herself to issues of child welfare at the state, national and international level
Biographical Note
Katharine F. Lenroot, child welfare leader and the third Chief of the United States Children's Bureau (1934-1951) was born in Superior, Wisconsin on March 8, 1891 to Irvin Luther and Clara C. Lenroot. From early on, her father's political career made Lenroot aware of social and political issues. Admitted to the bar in 1898, Irvine was elected to the Wisconsin state legislature in 1901. After his service in Wisconsin until 1907, he was elected to the national House of Representatives from 1909 to 1918, and to the Senate from 1918 to 1927. During her father's terms in the state legislature, Katharine frequently stayed in Madison, and after graduating from Superior State Normal School in 1909 she deferred entering college for a year to join him in Washington, D.C.
Affected by her father's engagement in the regulation of Wisconsin railroads, Lenroot majored in economics and minored in sociology at the University of Wisconsin, Madison. There, she was most influenced by the economist John R. Commons, who often required his students to conduct research for new legislation. Lenroot prepared a brief and testified before the legislative committee of Wisconsin to support minimum wage legislation, which did not exist in the United States at the time. With continued interest in minimum wage legislation, Lenroot decided to take the civil service examination, and upon completion of her B.A. in 1912, she began her professional career in 1913 as a deputy of the Industrial Commission of Wisconsin, of which Commons was a member. Lenroot, hired as an assistant to Emma O. Lundberg, with whom she would work closely in the following years, surveyed living costs in relation to the state's new minimum wage law.
In 1914, Lenroot and Lundberg both left Wisconsin to join the United States Children's Bureau in Washington, D.C. The bureau had been created only two years earlier by President Taft, with Julia Lathrop as the first Chief (1912-1921), and Lundberg was appointed the first Director of the Social Service Division. Through a civil service examination, Lenroot started as a special investigator in the division, and was soon promoted to Assistant Director. Lenroot mostly studied juvenile courts, and issues of unmarried mothers and their children. Illegitimacy as a Child Welfare Problem (1920, 1922) and Juvenile Courts at Work (1925), both co-authored with Lundberg, cover some of her research from this period. In June 1921, Lenroot became Director of the Editorial Division, and in November 1922, at the age of 30, she was advanced to Assistant Chief of the Bureau, serving under Grace Abbott, the second Chief (1922-1934). On Abbott's retirement, in December 1934 Lenroot was appointed the third Chief by President Roosevelt, and remained in the position until 1951. In 1935, she also served as the president of the National Conference of Social Work.
Under the FDR administration, the responsibilities of the Children's Bureau expanded significantly. Lenroot, along with Assistant Chief Martha Eliott and former Chief Grace Abbott designed and advocated the Title IV, or the Aid to Dependent Children, and Title V and VII of the Social Security Act of 1935. The act authorized the Children's Bureau to administer federal grants-in-aid to the states for maternal and child health and child welfare, and services to disabled children. Later, the bureau also became responsible for the child labor provisions of the Fair Labor Standards Act of 1938. From 1943 to 1947 the bureau administered the Emergency Maternity and Infant Care Program for soldiers' wives and children. To obtain the cooperation of professional and citizens' groups, the bureau also took the initiative in forming the National Commission on Children in War-time, which became the basis of Mid-century White House Conference on Children and Youth.
After the war, in July 1946, the Children's Bureau went through administrative reorganization, and was transferred from the Department of Labor, the home of the bureau since 1913, to the Federal Security Agency. While the child labor function remained in the Department of Labor, the bureau maintained its other functions, but the place of the Children's Bureau in the federal government continued to be a concern for Lenroot in the later years.
Lenroot's responsibility as the head of the Children's Bureau was not limited to national child welfare, and one of her contributions in the post-war years was the creation of the United Nations International Children's Emergency Fund. In 1946, when the Economic and Social Council established the Temporary Social Commission of the United Nations, Lenroot was appointed as its Secretary to establish a new organization within the UN to specialize in child welfare. By then, Lenroot and the Children's Bureau already had considerable international experience. Lenroot's involvement in inter-American child welfare had begun in 1924, when she attended the Fourth Pan-American Child Congress in Chile. Fluent in Spanish, she was the chair of the U.S. delegation in the Fifth (Cuba, 1927), Sixth (Peru, 1930), and Ninth (Venezuela, 1948) Pan-American Child Congresses, and served as the president in the Eighth (U.S., 1942) Pan-American Child Congress. Lenroot was also a member of the Advisory Committee of the Traffic in Women and Children established by the League of Nations Council in 1922. From 1937 through 1939, she represented the U.S. on the Advisory Committee of Social Questions of the League of Nations. Drawing on her international and inter-American experiences, Lenroot served as the U.S. representative on the executive board of UNICEF from 1947 to 1951, and played a significant role in setting the direction of the new organization.
Lenroot retired from the Children's Bureau in 1951, a year after serving as the Secretary of the Mid-century White House Conference on Children and Youth. She was succeeded by Martha Eliott, who had been her Assistant Chief since the mid-1930s. For her nearly 37 years of service in the bureau, Lenroot was honored with the Federal Security Agency Distinguished Civilian Service Award. Among numerous other awards she received in the course of her career were the University of Chicago's Rosenberg Medal (1942), the Gold Medal of the National Institute of Social Sciences (1947), and the Survey Award (1950). She also received honorary doctorates from the University of Wisconsin (1938), her alma mater, Russell Sage College (1948), Tulane University (1948), Western Reserve University (1951), and Boston University (1952). For her engagement in inter-American child welfare, a number of organizations in Latin America honored her as well.
Until the early 1970s, Lenroot continued to be active in local, national and international child welfare work. After her retirement from the federal government, Lenroot moved from Washington D.C. to Hartsdale, New York, and shared a home with Emma O. Lundberg until Lundberg's death in 1954. Lenroot frequently traveled to attend conferences and to give speeches and lectures before various audiences. Among the organizations Lenroot worked closely with were the Child Welfare League of America and the International Union for Child Welfare. She also kept in contact with the staff of the Children's Bureau such as Martha Eliott, discussing the role and the future of the bureau. After moving to Princeton, New Jersey in 1960, she served at the New Jersey State Board of Child Welfare and at the advisory council of Graduate School of Social Work at Rutgers University. From 1962 to 1963, Lenroot also worked as a consultant to the UNICEF, drafting their field manual and traveling to Geneva.
Katharine F. Lenroot died on February 10, 1982; she was 90 years old.
Scope and Content
Katharine F. Lenroot is best known as the third Chief of the United States Children's Bureau, and materials dating from her service at the bureau (1915-1951) comprise the largest part of this collection. Lenroot continued to devote herself to the field of child welfare after her retirement, and the second-largest part of the collection dates from 1951 to the early 1970s. A few materials from her Wisconsin years are present. The Papers include typescripts and reprints of Lenroot's speeches and writings, her research files, correspondence with various individuals and organizations engaged in the field of child welfare. The collection also contains reports, bulletins, and photographs from conferences organized by the Children's Bureau or attended by Lenroot. Very little purely personal material is found in this collection.
The media covered Lenroot and the Children's Bureau on various occasions, and the Papers include a large number of newspaper and magazine clippings. Please note that newspaper clippings are in fragile condition. Official biographical notes and personnel records prepared by the bureau are another biographical source included in the Papers. An overview of Lenroot's career at the bureau and the network she built in the course are represented in the biographical notes, clippings, correspondence, and photographs from her retirement in 1951.
Also included in the Papers are certificates of honorary degrees, numerous awards and honorary memberships that Lenroot received from both within and outside the U.S. In addition to the certificates, some folders contain correspondence, photographs, and speeches related to the ceremonies.
Along with Lenroot's own writings and printed materials, this collection contains publications by other individuals and child welfare organizations, which Lenroot filed for her own reference; reprints, journals, pamphlets, and clippings. The largest set of works is by Emma O. Lundberg, a co-worker and a close friend of Lenroot's since the 1910s. The collection also includes original manuscripts of Burton Jesse Hendrick, the author of Andrew Carnegie's biography.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in four series:
Series I. Writings and Speeches, 1911-1973
Subseries I.1. Indexed Speeches, Articles, and Radio, 1920-1951
Subseries I.2. Speeches and Writings, 1911-1970
Subseries I.3. Writings and Reports, 1915-1962
Subseries I.4. Printed Materials, 1918-1973
Subseries I.5. Writings--By Burton Jesse Hendrick, 1928-1940s
Series II. Professional, 1924-1974
Subseries II.1 Biographical, 1934-1972
Subseries II.2. United States Children's Bureau, 1924-1970
Subseries II.3. International Activities, 1924-1974
Subseries II.4. Special Events, 1930-1961
Series III. Correspondence, 1928-1973
Series IV. Subject Files, 1909-1973
Subseries IV.1. Individuals, 1925-1973
Subseries IV.2. Subjects and Organizations, 1912-1970
Subseries IV.3. Personal, 1909-1971
Subjects
National Conference of Social Work (U.S.); Pan American Child Congress.; United States.--Children's Bureau.; United States.--Social Security Administration.; UNICEF.; Mid-century White House Conference on Children and Youth (1950--Washington, D.C.); White House Conference on Childnre in a Democracy (1939-1940--Washington, D.C.); Abbott, Edith, 1876-1957.; Abbott, Grace, 1878-1939.; Eliot, Martha M. (Martha May), b.1891.; Hendrick, Burton Jesse, 1870-1949.; Lenroot, Katharine F. (Katharine Frederica), 1891-1982.; Lundberg, Emma O. (Emma Octavia).; Carnegie, Andrew, 1835-1919.; Child labor.; Children--Legal status, laws, etc.; Child welfare.; Social security.; Children.; Working class families.
Access Restrictions
This collection has no restrictions.
This collection is located off-site. You will need to request this material at least twenty-four (24) hours in advance to use the collection in the Rare Book and Manuscript Library reading room.
Acquisition
1970 M-70 New York School of Social Work Transfer
Selected Related Material-- At Columbia
Reminiscences of Katharine Fredrica Lenroot: Oral History, 1965 Oral History Research Office Collection, Columbia University Library
Selected Related Material-- At Other Repositories
Records of the United States Children's Bureau, 1908-1969 (Record Group 102), National Archives and Records Administration
- Series I: Writings and Speeches, 1911-1973
  The writings contained within the collection are both those of Lenroot and those by other individuals and organizations.
  - Subseries I.1: Indexed Speeches, Articles and Radio, 1920-1951
    This subseries contains Lenroot's speeches, articles, and radio talks dating from her times in the United States Children's Bureau. Although Lenroot began her service in the bureau in 1915, this subseries does not include materials prior to 1920. This material is arranged chronologically; an index, original to the material, accompanies each set of folders.
    - Speeches and Articles, 1920-1929, (4 Folders) (Box 1, Folder 1 to 4)
    - Speeches, Articles and Radio, 1930-1934, (4 Folders) (Box 1, Folder 5 to 8)
    - Speeches, Articles and Radio, 1935 January-July (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Speeches, Articles and Radio, 1935 August-December (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Speeches, Articles and Radio, 1936-1937 (1 binder) (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Speeches, Articles and Radio, 1938, (4 Folders) (Box 2, Folder 3 to 6)
    - Speeches, Articles and Radio, 1939 (1 binder) (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Speeches, Articles and Radio, 1940, (4 Folders) (Box 3, Folder 2 to 5)
    - Radio Series--“Raising a President,” 1941, (3 Folders) (Box 3, Folder 6 to 8)
    - Speeches, Articles and Radio, 1941-1942, (7 Folders) (Box 4, Folder 1 to 7)
    - Speeches, Articles and Radio, 1943 (1 binder) (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Speeches, Articles and Radio, 1944-1945, (7 Folders) (Box 5, Folder 1 to 7)
    - Speeches, Articles and Radio, 1946 (1 binder) (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Speeches, Articles and Radio, 1947-1949, (7 Folders) (Box 6, Folder 1 to 7)
    - Speeches, Articles and Radio--No Index, 1950, (2 Folders) (Box 6, Folder 8 to 9)
    - Speeches, Articles and Radio, 1951, (2 Folders) (Box 7, Folder 1 to 2)
  - Subseries I.2: Speeches and Writings, 1911-1970
    Most of the speeches and writings included in this subseries were produced after Lenroot's retirement from the Children's Bureau, although some material dates from an earlier period. Among the pre-Washington materials are a minimum-wage legislation brief that Lenroot prepared as an undergraduate and her report for the Wisconsin Industrial Commission. This subseries is arranged chronologically, but does not include an index.
    - “Constitutionality of Proposed Law”--Brief for Minimum Wage Legislation in Wisconsin, 1911 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Wisconsin Industrial Commission, 1913-1916, (3 Folders) (Box 7, Folder 4 to 6)
    - “The Legal Status and Social Condition of Women and Children in the United States,” 1925 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Wisconsin State Legislature, 1935 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - National Conference of Social Work, 1935 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - International Conference on Social Work, London, 1936 (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - General Council of Congregational and Christian Churches, 1938 (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - National Conference of Social Work, 1940 (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - “Changes in Social Welfare during the Decade 1931-1940,” 1940 (Box 7, Folder 13)
    - Unfulfilled Autobiography--Correspondence with Publisher, 1940 (Box 7, Folder 14)
    - “Day Care of Children of Women Employed in War Industries”--Statement for the House Committee Investigating National Defense Migration, 1942 (Box 7, Folder 15)
    - Church Groups--List of Speeches and Articles Given by Lenroot in Connection with, 1945-1950 (Box 7, Folder 16)
    - Unitarian Convocation, 1950 (Box 7, Folder 17)
    - Interagency Conference on Personality Development in Children, 1951 (Box 7, Folder 18)
    - National Council of Negro Women, 1952 (Box 7, Folder 19)
    - New York State Welfare Conference, 1951 (Box 7, Folder 20)
    - Educational Forum-- Manuscript, 1951-1952 (Box 7, Folder 21)
    - Cornell University--New York Hospital School of Nursing, 1952 (Box 7, Folder 22)
    - New York School of Social Work--Lecture Series, 1952 (Box 7, Folder 23)
    - Maryland State Conference on Social Welfare, 1952 (Box 7, Folder 24)
    - Lincoln Grade School--Wisconsin, 1952 (Box 7, Folder 25)
    - Protestant Family Welfare, 1952 (Box 7, Folder 26)
    - Church Conference of Social Work, 1952 (Box 7, Folder 27)
    - Delaware Commission on Children and Welfare, 1952 (Box 7, Folder 28)
    - Introduction for Frank Richardson’s Girls Only-- Manuscript and Correspondence, 1953 (Box 7, Folder 29)
    - New York Diet Kitchen Association, 1953 (Box 7, Folder 30)
    - Greater Miami Council of Churches, 1953 (Box 7, Folder 31)
    - Boston Congregational Club, 1953 (Box 7, Folder 32)
    - University of Florida--College Textbook--Correspondence, 1953 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - General Council of Congregational and Christian Churches, 1954 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Rotary Club, 1956 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Kew Forest School Association, 1956 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Community Service Society, 1957 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - New York State Charities Aid Association, 1957 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Nebraska Welfare Association and Iowa Governor’s Conference, 1958 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - National Association of Congregational and Christian Churches, 1958 (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - “Clara Beyer and the Children’s Bureau,” 1958 (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - Book Review of Sophia Robison’s Juvenile Delinquency-- Manuscript and Correspondence, 1960 (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - “Provisions for Children in the 1935 Economic and Social Security Program,”1960 (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - Inter-American Children’s Institute, 1961 (Box 8, Folder 12)
    - “Community Organization for Day Care,” 1961 (Box 8, Folder 13)
    - Rutgers University, 1961-1962 (Box 8, Folder 14)
    - New Jersey Association of Social Workers, 1967 (Box 8, Folder 15)
    - Book Review of Charles Loring Brace's,Dangerous Classes of New York-- Manuscript and Correspondence, 1968 (Box 8, Folder 16)
    - “Notes for Paper of Role Relations in a Mental Health Program,” 1969 (Box 8, Folder 17)
    - Guest Editorial for Child Welfare 1970 (Box 8, Folder 18)
    - Introduction to Mary Carpenter’s Juvenile Delinquents Research Materials, circa 1970 (Box 8, Folder 19)
  - Subseries I.3: Writings and Reports, 1915-1962
    This subseries consists of published reports and articles by Lenroot. Studies that Lenroot conducted with the Children's Bureau in the late 1910s appear in this subseries. The materials are arranged alphabetically by title.
    - Advisory Committee on Education--Report--Lenroot as Member, 1938 (Box 8, Folder 20)
    - Annals of the American Academy of Political and Social Science, 1921-1940 (Box 8, Folder 21)
    - Chart on Curriculum Materials Used in Church Schools-- for the National Association of Congregational and Christian Churches,circa 1950s (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - “Children of the Depression”--Social Service Review 1935 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Child Welfare as a Field of Social Work Practice-- Child Welfare League--Edited by Lenroot, 1959 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Department of State Bulletin, 1952-1962 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - “Education’s Part in the Development of Healthy Personality in Children and Youth”--Educational Forum, 1952 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - “Henrietta Szold: Social Pioneer”--Hadassah Newsletter 1945 (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - “National Education Objectives in a Post-War Program for Children and Youth”--Iowa Law Review, 1945 (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - “The Child as the World’s Best Hope for Peace”--Methodist Woman, 1952 (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - “The Children’s Year Program as Related to Children in Institutions,National Conference on the Education of Truant, Backward, Dependent and Delinquent Children Proceedings 1919 (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - “The Child, the Family, and the Court”--National Probation Association Proceedings 1928 (Box 9, Folder 11)
    - “Working Together for Children”--for the International Union for Child Welfare, 1956 (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - Subseries I.4: Printed Materials, 1918-1973
    Within this small subseries are articles and publications by other individuals and organizations in the field of child welfare with whom Lenroot often worked closely. The folders have been arranged alphabetically by author.
    - Abbott, Edith, 1940-1941 (Box 9, Folder 14)
    - Abbott, Grace, 1923-1924 (Box 9, Folder 15)
    - American Public Welfare Association, 1963 (Box 9, Folder 16)
    - Child Welfare League of America, 1955 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Eisenberg, Leon, 1960 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - International Child Welfare Review 1962-1963 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Lathrop, Julia, 1918, (2 Folders) (Box 10, Folder 4 to 5)
    - Lesser, Arthur J., 1969 (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - Lundberg, Emma O.
      - Child Dependency in the United States, 1932 (Box 10, Folder 7)
      - “Foster Care of Dependent Children,” 1930s (Box 10, Folder 8)
      - New York Temporary Emergency Relief Administration, 1931-1934 (Box 10, Folder 9)
      - New York Temporary Emergency Relief Administration, 1931-1934 (3 bound volumes) (Box 11, Folder 1 to 3)
    - Michigan Joint Legislative Committee to Study Foster Care, 1951 (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - National Child Labor Committee, 1954 (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - National Committee for Children and Youth, 1966 (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - National Conference of Social Work, 1973 (Box 12, Folder 4)
    - New York School of Social Work, 1961 (Box 12, Folder 5)
    - Perlman, Selig--on John Rogers Commons, 1945 (Box 12, Folder 6)
    - Rees, John R., 1966 (Box 12, Folder 7)
    - Simons, Savilla Millis, 1965 (Box 12, Folder 8)
    - Smith, Caineweaver, 1942 (Box 12, Folder 9)
    - Social Work, 1962-1963 (Box 12, Folder 10)
    - Social Work Process 1954 (Box 12, Folder 11)
    - Survey 1929-1930 (Box 12, Folder 12)
    - UNICEF News, 1965-1973 (Box 12, Folder 13)
    - United States Children’s Bureau
      - General--Reprints, 1913, 1946 (Box 12, Folder 14)
      - Pamphlets, 1934-1942 (Box 12, Folder 15)
      - Children, 1957 (Box 12, Folder 16)
      - “Children’s Bureau during World War II,” 1945 (Box 12, Folder 17)
      - “For Our Children in Wartime,” 1942 (Box 12, Folder 18)
      - “Goals for Children,” 1960-1961 (Box 12, Folder 19)
      - “History of Public Relief”--Typescript, mid-1930s (Box 12, Folder 20)
      - “Policy Manual,” 1951 (Box 12, Folder 21)
    - United States Department of Health, Education, and Welfare, 1965 (Box 12, Folder 22)
    - Witte, Ernest, 1954-1959 (Box 12, Folder 23)
    - Wright, Helen R., 1949 (Box 12, Folder 24)
  - Subseries I.5: Writings-- By Burton Jesse Hendrick, 1928-1940s